<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-15T02:51:58+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">My PhD Confirmation</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2025/my-phd-confirmation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My PhD Confirmation"/><published>2025-09-09T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-09T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2025/my-phd-confirmation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2025/my-phd-confirmation/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve completed my PhD confirmation-the first major milestone in my research journey at <a href="https://a2i2.deakin.edu.au/">Deakin Applied Artificial Intelligence Initiative</a>. My thesis, <strong>“Towards Reliable Large Language Models for Open-ended Question Answering”</strong>, aims to explore how we can build more trustworthy AI systems that can handle open-ended questions effectively. Reflecting on this past year, I’ve found research to be both challenging and inspiring. Coming from industry, where the focus is often on <em>“making things work”</em>, I’ve learned that research goes one step further-striving to make things work in a new, creative, and impactful way.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b11_phd_confirmation/confirmation-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b11_phd_confirmation/confirmation-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b11_phd_confirmation/confirmation-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b11_phd_confirmation/confirmation.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I believe two qualities are especially important in this journey: the <strong>persistence</strong> to keep learning and working hard, and the <strong>creativity</strong> to explore new ideas. Their importance shifts over time-at the early stage, as I am now, persistence is crucial for building a solid foundation, while creativity becomes increasingly vital as the research matures.</p> <p>Looking ahead, I’m excited to continue developing both qualities and to take the next steps in shaping my research journey.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="work"/><category term="work"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson learned from the first year of PhD]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My first Triathlon</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2025/my-first-triathlon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My first Triathlon"/><published>2025-04-13T13:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-13T13:36:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2025/my-first-triathlon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2025/my-first-triathlon/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b10_first_tri/finish_line.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b10_first_tri/finish_line.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b10_first_tri/finish_line.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b10_first_tri/finish_line.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I had always hesitated to join a triathlon—until I started using a bike for daily commuting in Australia. That simple routine slowly built my confidence on two wheels. Then, during Easter 2025, I returned to my home country and completed my very first triathlon (Olympic distance: 1.5km :swimmer:, 40km :bicyclist: and 10km :runner:) at the <a href="https://aquawarriors.com.vn/">Aqua Warriors Series</a>, held in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%E1%BA%A1_Long">Ha Long, Quang Ninh</a>. It was a memorable and eye-opening experience that left me not only with great stories but also many valuable reflections.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="1-triathlon-is-a-challenging-but-rewarding-sport">1. Triathlon is a Challenging but Rewarding Sport</h2> <p>Triathlon is both physically demanding and deeply fulfilling. The challenge lies in the discipline and structured training it requires—<strong>balancing swimming, cycling, and running</strong> isn’t something you can do on a whim. It takes consistent effort and careful planning.</p> <p>But the rewards are worth it. Competing in a triathlon feels like the <strong>culmination of a long, disciplined journey</strong>, and the <strong>race-day atmosphere</strong> often brings out the best in us. Surrounded by other athletes with high spirits, we are naturally pushed forward—<strong>mentally and physically</strong>. The support on race day, from volunteers and spectators, makes the experience much more enjoyable and energizing compared to solo training.</p> <p>To perform well, two key things matter: a <strong>strong, positive mindset and a well-thought-out race strategy</strong>. Staying relaxed but focused helps maintain motivation, especially when the going gets tough. A good strategy should break the race down lap by lap, including transitions—because in endurance sports, <strong>consistency is crucial</strong>. Finding and maintaining a steady pace is often the key to a personal best. However, since triathlon involves switching between disciplines, it’s common to struggle with pacing early in each segment. That’s why it’s important to <strong>listen to your body closely in the first 10 minutes of each leg</strong>—roughly the first 300m swim, 5km bike, and 2km run—to avoid false start and allow your breathing to stabilize and your body to adjust to the new rhythm.</p> <p>Given how demanding triathlon training is, and how limited our time, energy, and youth can be, I truly <em>value every opportunity</em> I get to participate in this sport.</p> <blockquote> <p>Competing is the result of training, expressed in a boosted spirit. Pace achievements:</p> <ul> <li>:swimmer: <strong>2:40</strong> /100m</li> <li>:bicyclist: <strong>30.8</strong> km/h</li> <li>:runner: <strong>4:51</strong> /km</li> </ul> </blockquote> <hr/> <h2 id="2-cycling-is-an-expensive-and-dangerous-sport">2. Cycling is an Expensive and Dangerous Sport</h2> <p>Among the three disciplines in triathlon, cycling arguably has <strong>the most significant impact</strong> on overall performance. The ride segment is long and intense, and a strong bike leg can make a huge difference in the final results. That’s why, if you’re serious about improving, investing in <strong>a good bike isn’t just optional — it’s essential</strong>.</p> <p>In my own experience, the gap between using a basic bike and a high-performance one is massive. A better bike doesn’t just make the ride smoother; it also opens the door to more advanced techniques like drafting, which professional triathletes use for over 80% of the course to conserve energy and maintain high speeds. <strong>A quality road bike typically costs around $2,000–$4,000 USD</strong> — a big investment, but one that makes a noticeable difference in performance and comfort during training and racing. During my first Olympic-distance triathlon, I rode a cheap rental bike and still managed an average speed of 30.8 km/h over the 40 km course. With a high-quality bike set up properly for aerodynamics and wind protection, maintaining an average speed of 35 km/h becomes much more achievable and sustainable — even comfortable with good form and training.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b10_first_tri/cycling.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b10_first_tri/cycling.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b10_first_tri/cycling.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b10_first_tri/cycling.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My first 40km race bike ride (pace: 30.8 km/h) </div> <p>But cycling isn’t just costly — it’s also <strong>the most dangerous part of triathlon</strong>. Training often requires <strong>long-distance rides at high speeds</strong>, sometimes on open roads or in unpredictable weather. The margin for error is small. From what I’ve experienced and seen, mastering bike handling skills is absolutely vital: keeping a firm grip on the handlebars, knowing when and how to brake, and avoiding unnecessary hand movements can significantly affect both safety and performance. I’ve witnessed how unforgiving the sport can be — one wrong move at high speed can easily lead to a crash — but I’ve also seen how rewarding it is when someone gains full control and confidence on the bike.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="3-to-follow-a-sport-long-term-progress-is-the-key">3. To Follow a Sport Long-Term, Progress is the Key</h2> <p>At first, I believed that passion was the most important factor in staying committed to a sport. But over time, I’ve come to realize that <strong>simply liking something isn’t enough</strong>. If we want to stick with a sport for the long haul, <strong>the most crucial element is progress</strong>. Without progress, it’s easy to lose motivation — even the strongest passion can fade when things start to feel stagnant.</p> <p>Progress doesn’t have to happen quickly. It’s not about a few days or weeks, especially in sports that are technically demanding like swimming. Sometimes, it takes months or even years to truly feel improvement. Though I’m still relatively new to swimming and cycling, I’ve been running for over four years, and I’ve started to notice some shared patterns across all three disciplines. Each sport may engage different muscle groups and require different techniques, but they all demand <strong>endurance, resilience, and mental strength</strong> — qualities that triathlon trains better than almost anything else.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b10_first_tri/progress_is_key-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b10_first_tri/progress_is_key-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b10_first_tri/progress_is_key-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b10_first_tri/progress_is_key.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Better every day is the key to long-term success in a sport </div> <p>One insight I’ve found especially valuable is <strong>the role of relaxation in training</strong>. To build endurance and improve technique, being able to sense and control how your body moves — especially when relaxed — is critical. The more I train, the more I notice how important <strong>the hip flexor muscles</strong> are. Learning to release tension in that area has improved my overall performance by more than 10% across all three sports. That kind of subtle, gradual improvement is what keeps me going.</p> <hr/> <p>Looking back, <strong>completing my first triathlon was more than just crossing a finish line</strong> — it marked the beginning of a deeper journey. <strong>A journey of discipline, discovery, and self-improvement</strong>. Through the swim, the ride, and the run, I learned not just about endurance, but about myself. Triathlon isn’t just about being physically fit; it’s about building patience, mental strength, and the ability to adapt. The sport is demanding, yes, but that’s what makes the rewards so deeply personal.</p> <p>Whether you’re just starting out or already deep into your triathlon journey, I believe progress — no matter how small — is the true motivator. Keep moving forward, stay curious, and embrace the challenges along the way. Because in the end, it’s not just about <strong>becoming a better athlete — it’s about becoming a better version of yourself</strong>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b10_first_tri/conclusion.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b10_first_tri/conclusion.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b10_first_tri/conclusion.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b10_first_tri/conclusion.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> </div> <p><strong>If you’re considering trying triathlon for the first time — just go for it</strong>. You don’t need the best gear or years of experience to get started. A rented bike, a steady mindset, and a willingness to learn can take you further than you think. Start where you are, train consistently, and you’ll surprise yourself. And if you ever feel stuck, just remember: <strong>progress is still progress, no matter how slow it feels</strong>.</p> <hr/> <p><em>I wrote this based on my own experience and ideas — with a little help from <a href="https://openai.com/chatgpt">ChatGPT</a> along the way.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sports"/><category term="run"/><category term="swim"/><category term="life"/><category term="ride"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson learned from my first Triathlon]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking back at My 20s</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2024/lookback-my-20s/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking back at My 20s"/><published>2024-10-15T09:55:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-15T09:55:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2024/lookback-my-20s</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2024/lookback-my-20s/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b9_lookback_20s/cover-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b9_lookback_20s/cover-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b9_lookback_20s/cover-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b9_lookback_20s/cover.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Turning 30, I look back at my 20s with youthful thoughts and think about how I could have done better if given another chance. Writing this is not to express regret, but rather to draw lessons for the exciting journeys ahead. Below are things I did, or did but not completely, not including countless things I thought about or planned but did not do.</p> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip">TIP</h5> <p>For me, the 20s are the best time to invest in self-development, maximize experiences, and seek opportunities to build a dream life.</p> </blockquote> <p>In general, planning your life early is very important as it directly influences how we think and act daily. Long-term plans (5, 10 or more years) don’t need to be overly detailed, as we lack much information to make decisions. But break them down into short-term, detailed plans (&lt;1 year), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SMART_criteria">SMART</a> to strive for the present, achieve the first solid steps, and gradually optimize to open up new opportunities.</p> <p>This can be divided into three main categories as follows.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="1-preparing-and-searching-for-desired-jobs">1. Preparing and Searching for Desired Jobs</h2> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Graduate with a degree in your favorite field</strong>: If you can choose a major aligned with your passion right after high school, that’s lucky. If you actively seek information from high school, your chances of success increase. To be honest, when choosing a university, I only thought I would study engineering at a good technical school, but luckily, I studied well enough to be “selected”. and that choice hasn’t been too wrong until now.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Master a programming language earlier</strong>: During my university days, no one told me this. Although it is eventually taught, having an early learning plan means you value it more, learn it better, and have more career opportunities even as a student.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Learn English seriously and early</strong>: I started learning English in grade 3, but only knew about certifications like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TOEIC">TOEIC</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_English_Language_Testing_System">IELTS</a> when entering university. When working, I began to stumble with English communication. As a student, many programs and scholarships are available for those with good English, but not for me. Although I can now work in international environments, I advise 20-somethings to improve conversational English or obtain multi-skill certifications like IELTS.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Experiencing different learning styles</strong>: We could try to learn in many different ways (e.g. books, videos, podcast) to find the most effective method for yourself. Learning is a lifelong career, so a good foundation can take us far.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Take all opportunities</strong>: We often fear that taking on multiple part-time jobs or experiences will affect other work or time management. Utilizing work opportunities, we can increase income, gain exposure to various environments, and enhance time management skills, making us value time much more.</p> </li> </ul> <blockquote class="block-warning"> <h5 id="warning">WARNING</h5> <p>When young, I found it’s easy to lose discipline with too much free time.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h2 id="2-building-plans-and-financial-management">2. Building Plans and Financial Management</h2> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Earn and invest early, especially as a student</strong>: Earning, spending, and managing finances are crucial throughout life. Starting early gives us more experience and better management later.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Living Independently</strong>: Moving out early fosters independence. This is a time of great <strong>“freedom”</strong>, but also when you must actively manage your life. Sometimes, it will be tough without support, but it just comes a bit sooner. The older I get, the more I realize the truth in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_symbols_of_Vietnam">“Independence, Liberty, Happiness”</a>: independence and freedom are essential for happiness.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Thinking About Your First House</strong>: The first house is special, both a home and an asset. Generally, its value increases over time. Thinking about it early motivates work spirit and seizing earning opportunities. Besides financial aspects, the first house has great emotional value. It provides a sense of security for the family and boosts determination at work. When owning a house, you’ll care for it much more than a rented place, understanding housing issues and the home-buying process, which improves future decisions.</p> </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>The first house is special, both a home and an asset.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h2 id="3-finding-passions-and-lifestyle">3. Finding Passions and Lifestyle</h2> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Sports</strong>: The primary benefit of sports is building a good fitness foundation for later. It also creates necessary excitement to relieve stress and opens many opportunities to socialize and meet new friends. If possible, I wish I had started swimming and running earlier.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Playing Musical Instruments</strong>: Life would be more interesting if I could play an instrument like guitar, ukulele, or piano, to play and sing in my free time. I tried playing guitar, but it requires much time to play well. As we grow older, we have more priorities, so starting early is better.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Commit Fully to Your Work (Quality &gt; Quantity)</strong>: It’s easy to do things superficially, just for the experience, leaving time for other things. However, to succeed in life and work, this mindset is crucial. I see this in a few examples:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Exploratory Travel vs. Experiential Travel</strong>: I believe exploring, immersing in remote areas, and experiencing local culture makes a trip memorable. Simply passing through, strolling, and checking in might not be enough.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Finding Your Passion</strong>: True passion involves challenging yourself and improving daily by reaching your limits, having a development plan, and a companion. Passion stems from interests, but when we are genuinely passionate something, we want to approach it in interesting ways. It can start as a habit, e.g., daily training, but I can make it more enjoyable by trying a different method, a new route, or simply a different pace.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Choices Are the Greatest Asset</strong>: We are <strong>“truly free”</strong> when we have many choices. I suggest investing in being wealthy in choices, not just money. This means job options (e.g., not being tied to one place or job) or living places (e.g., not being bound to one location, region, or country). Moreover, never be in a situation with no other choices.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>The Power of Habits</strong>: We’ve heard much about the power of habits, but to create the most “power,” maintaining the habit is key. Building a habit for a short time isn’t too hard, but maintaining and scaling it over a longer period (months, a year) isn’t simple. It requires proper motivation and high discipline. In practice, I always try to start slow and steady, ensuring I don’t waste time turning back and can maintain it for a certain period before accelerating with more information.</p> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="experience"/><category term="life"/><category term="skill"/><category term="review"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Looking back at my 20s from my 30s' perspective]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My first award in sports</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2024/my-first-award-in-sports/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My first award in sports"/><published>2024-09-29T15:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T15:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2024/my-first-award-in-sports</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2024/my-first-award-in-sports/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/prize_cover-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/prize_cover-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/prize_cover-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/prize_cover.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>One year ago, I couldn’t even imagine participating in <a href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/2023-lessons-learned/">open water swimming</a>. Fast forward to this year, I’ve “overcome countless obstacles” to achieve my first sports title. I secured a <strong>top 3 position in my age group for the Olympic distance (1.5km :swimmer:, 10km :runner:)</strong> at the <a href="https://aquawarriors.com.vn/">Aqua Warriors Series</a>, held in late September 2024 in <a href="https://vi.wikipedia.org/wiki/V%C3%A2n_%C4%90%E1%BB%93n">Van Don, Quang Ninh</a>. This event has significantly boosted my spirit and changed my mindset about physical training.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="1-why-open-water">1. Why Open Water?</h2> <p>Open water swimming presents a different set of challenges compared to the endurance difficulties I faced while <a href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/my-first-marathon/">conquering various running distances</a>. It involves a significant psychological aspect when swimming in open water, combined with the technical demands of swimming. Through this journey, I discovered my next favorite sport (after running) and have plans to excel in it.</p> <p>Before deciding to swim in open water, around late 2023, I taught myself to swim by watching YouTube videos, especially channels like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@ThayChienDayBoi">Thay Chien Day Boi</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@yeuboiloiclub">Yeu Boi Loi</a>. I managed to swim both breaststroke and freestyle for a few hundred meters. My best performance was <strong>:swimmer: 1km freestyle in 28 minutes</strong>. Reflecting on this, I identified several mistakes, including:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Incorrect arm strokes</strong>: failing to push enough water</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Poor body posture</strong>: high head and sinking legs</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Inefficient breathing</strong>: not deep enough and raising my body too high</p> </li> </ul> <p>Due to these improper techniques and poor water feel, there were weeks when I was lazy (less than 3 sessions per week), and my performance even declined during this period.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="2-key-checkpoints">2. Key Checkpoints</h2> <ul> <li> <p><strong>19-12-2023</strong>: Registered for my first swimming class with coach <strong>Thanh Lucky</strong></p> </li> <li> <p><strong>01-02-2024</strong>: :swimmer: <strong>1km</strong> with a pace of <strong>2:45</strong></p> </li> <li> <p><strong>05-03-2024</strong>: :swimmer: <strong>1.5km</strong> with a pace of <strong>3:00</strong></p> </li> <li> <p><strong>07-03-2024</strong>: :swimmer: <strong>2km</strong> with a pace of <strong>2:55</strong></p> </li> <li> <p><strong>31-03-2024</strong>: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=7025390887516182&amp;set=gm.1036806554264004&amp;idorvanity=258194625458538">Red River Warrior</a></p> </li> </ul> <p>This was my first open water swimming event. I decided to register in early January and started taking lessons with my first swimming coach to learn the correct techniques and fix my mistakes.</p> <p>However, it wasn’t easy at all. I considered quitting on the day before the competition, thinking it was too risky. During my three practice sessions in the river, I never completed the course and always swam parallel to the shore, heading back early because the middle of the river was too overwhelming. It wasn’t until I pushed myself to swim 1km alone in the middle of the river (because I was slow) that my journey of conquering it truly began.</p> <p>The next day, despite swimming 3km in the competition, I felt like I could swim another lap afterward, which was very exciting for me. This was my first endurance swim in open water and a monumental personal victory, as I had doubted my ability to complete it.</p> <blockquote> <p>Achievement: <strong>:swimmer: 3km in 81 minutes</strong> (pace: <strong>2:42</strong>)</p> </blockquote> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/cbsh-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/cbsh-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/cbsh-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/cbsh.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My first 3km open water swim </div> <ul> <li><strong>14-04-2024</strong>: <a href="https://aquawarriors.com.vn/ha-long/">Aqua Warriors Ha Long</a></li> </ul> <p>This was my first time swimming in the sea and participating in a duathlon. I approached this event with the mindset of just completing it and chose a manageable distance that I could finish in about 2 hours (equivalent to the time it takes to run a half marathon), which was the <strong>Olympic distance (1.5km :swimmer:, 10km :runner:)</strong>.</p> <p>The day before the competition, seeing the calm waves at Hon Gai beach, I thought about trying the Full distance (3km :swimmer:, 15km :runner:) just to complete it. However, I believe I made the right choice in sticking to a distance that matched my training.</p> <p>Initially, I thought it would be easy to start slowly, take my time breathing, and maintain an endurance pace. However, with so many athletes, you could always be surrounded by different swimming and sighting styles. After getting kicked a few times and hit on the shoulder, I realized the harsh reality and had to continuously sight to find the best and most stable swimming path, which was much more tiring due to my limited technique.</p> <p>Venturing into the duathlon was truly exciting, and it was even more thrilling to feel confident without using a float and be considered for the top 3 in my age group. Although I only finished in the <strong>top 10</strong>, it was a significant encouragement for my “first time”.</p> <blockquote> <p>Unexpected Good Achievements:</p> <ul> <li>:swimmer: pace <strong>2:25</strong></li> <li>:runner: pace <strong>5:27</strong></li> </ul> </blockquote> <ul> <li> <p><strong>24-04-2024</strong>: Achieved a <strong>2:09 pace for 50m</strong></p> </li> <li> <p><strong>02-05-2024</strong>: Started training with my second swimming coach <strong>Hoang Swim</strong></p> </li> <li> <p><strong>15-05-2024</strong>: Achieved a <strong>2:06 pace for 100m</strong></p> </li> <li> <p><strong>17-06-2024</strong>: Achieved a <strong>1:40 pace for 50m</strong>.</p> </li> </ul> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip">TIP</h5> <p>During this time, I realized how important my legs were in swimming. Instead of occasional kicks to save energy, I switched to <strong>continuous kicking</strong>. It was less about the kick rate and more about feeling light, even, and keeping my hips afloat by straightening my body and engaging my core. Solutions for sinking legs included: looking down, taking low breaths, and stretching out. The <strong>legs became the key to body position and stroke rhythm</strong>, rather than the arms leading the movement as I previously thought.</p> </blockquote> <ul> <li> <p><strong>20-07-2024</strong>: Achieved a <strong>1:51 pace for 1km</strong>, 50m x 20 (resting 1 min per length)</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>18-08-2024</strong>: Achieved a <strong>2:05 pace for 1km</strong>, resting 1 min 30 (200m x 5)</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>21-08-2024</strong>: Achieved a <strong>2:08 pace for 1km</strong> (35m pool)</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>29-09-2024</strong>: <a href="https://aquawarriors.com.vn/">Aqua Warriors Van Don</a></p> </li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/aqua_vd_podium-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/aqua_vd_podium-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/aqua_vd_podium-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/aqua_vd_podium.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My second attempt at duathlon </div> <p>My second return to the Aquathlon with the same Olympic distance as in April, determined not to miss the top 3 age group position again. This goal was partly suggested by my second swimming coach, who believed I could swim much faster than when we first met. The timing of this event was perfect, right before my PhD studies in Australia, motivating me to participate and take my family along.</p> <p>Unlike the first time, I was better prepared this time. Beyond factors like race attire (shoes or sandals, what shirt or pants to wear, whether to wear goggles or a cap), the most crucial aspect was having a clear weekly training plan. A month before the race, I dedicated time to open water swimming and weekly brick sessions (simulating race day).</p> <p>I achieved my goal of finishing in the <strong>top 3 age group</strong> with the support and congratulations of my family, bringing me immense happiness.</p> <blockquote> <p>Surprising results - <strong>Top 3 age group (30-39)</strong>:</p> <ul> <li>:swimmer: pace <strong>2:35</strong>. Note that unlike April, this time the chip time included the swimming part and running on the sand, actual pace <strong>~2:20</strong>.</li> <li>:runner: pace <strong>5:20</strong></li> </ul> </blockquote> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/aqua_vd_result-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/aqua_vd_result-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/aqua_vd_result-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/aqua_vd_result.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Top 3 age group - Olympic distance </div> <blockquote class="block-warning"> <h5 id="warning">WARNING</h5> <p>Despite this, I felt my pre-race training intensity was insufficient and not as rigorous as the actual race, suggesting room for improvement. For instance, improving my swimming pace to <strong>2:10</strong> and standing up to avoid breaststroke and overtaking could enhance my performance. Additionally, independent time and less crowded lanes could help split the pack early. The running segment could also improve to a <strong>5:00 pace</strong>.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h2 id="3-my-coaches">3. My coaches</h2> <p>My <strong>first coach</strong> was a former competitive swimmer who taught at the pool in my neighborhood. He previously competed in the city’s team and participated in relays for <a href="https://www.ironman.com/">Ironman events</a>. He mentioned my technique needed to be “rebuilt from scratch” because although it looked correct, I needed to understand the principles or “feel” it. His methodical approach to teaching, from warm-ups and softening movements (legs, arms, shoulders) to flexibility exercises, significantly improved my skills. This foundation helped me complete my first two open water races. However, I felt it required a lot of time to progress and struggled with creating an effective training plan, so I sought another coach for my end-of-year event (Aqua Warriors Van Don).</p> <p>My <strong>second coach</strong> graduated as an engineer but switched to teaching swimming as a hobby. He was the coach of one of my <em>“run buddies”</em>. While he wasn’t as fast as a competitive swimmer (likely pacing around 1:30-1:40), his passion and enthusiasm stood out. Throughout the 16 sessions, I appreciated his detailed analysis and explanations of technique principles, constantly demonstrating for the students. Each session was an hour long, focused, beneficial, and not drawn-out.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/2nd_teacher-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/2nd_teacher-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/2nd_teacher-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/2nd_teacher.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My 2nd swimming coach. He also participated in Aqua Warriors Series. </div> <p>Moreover, his teaching was very up-to-date, incorporating insights from international YouTube channels (e.g. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@EffortlessSwimming">Effortless Swimming</a>). This approach introduced me to <strong>hip rotation (instead of shoulder rotation)</strong>, significantly improving my technique without dedicating excessive time to flexibility exercises. He set a <strong>sub-2 goal (1km in 20 minutes)</strong> for me, even though I never thought I could swim that fast. Despite the course being primarily freestyle, through asking questions, I also learned <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butterfly_stroke">butterfly</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backstroke">backstroke</a>. Currently, I can better feel the water, identify and correct mistakes, and set appropriate training plans.</p> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip-1">TIP</h5> <p>Many Swimming Teachers</p> </blockquote> <p>Unlike finding my first coach, I hesitated to seek a second coach, doubting the need for multiple instructors. Gradually, I observed that having multiple coaches is common for a sport requiring technical skills and training like swimming. Each coach has different methods and approaches, and being open to learning and practicing ensures progress. However, finding a dedicated coach helps you advance quicker and further.</p> <p>While I didn’t start with a coach, learning proper swimming techniques from the beginning is crucial. Early mistakes can be hard to correct later and may even cause muscle pain or injuries. Additionally, watching videos or getting feedback from others can help identify and correct mistakes, allowing you to find the technique that best suits you.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="4-summary-of-swimming-techniques">4. Summary of Swimming Techniques</h2> <p>The more I swim, the more I realize how crucial the feel of the water is in swimming. To swim more effortlessly and glide better, paying attention to this feeling is essential. However, achieving it isn’t easy, and not every swimming session provides that “feel”. Therefore, each time I swim, I note my observations, the techniques I try, and their effectiveness. If I’m lucky to have someone record a video of me in a quiet pool, I use it as a reference for further evaluation at home. This note-taking has resulted in quite a long list, and here I’ll try to summarize some key techniques.</p> <h3 id="a-freestyle">a. Freestyle</h3> <ul> <li> <p><strong>General Mindset</strong>: Relax and maintain the most streamlined position possible to reduce drag.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Breathing</strong>:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Importance: Most crucial aspect.</p> </li> <li> <p>Inhale through the nose slowly underwater, exhale fully through the mouth when turning to breathe.</p> </li> <li> <p>Rhythm: 2 or 3 strokes per breath. A 3-stroke rhythm is better for long-term balance, rotating the neck and shoulders evenly to avoid soreness. Being able to breathe on both sides (not necessarily in a 3-stroke rhythm) is equally important in open water swimming to reduce the need for frequent sighting.</p> </li> <li> <p>Deep Breathing: For endurance swimming, exhale fully underwater and open the mouth wide or inhale deeply when turning the head to maximize oxygen intake.</p> </li> <li> <p>Aim to keep the head as low as possible while breathing, ideally with one goggle in the water and one above, and just enough of the mouth above the water surface.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Arms</strong>:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Keep hands straight in all circumstances to maximize water contact.</p> </li> <li> <p>Arms should be shoulder-width apart, avoiding inward crossing that disrupts body alignment.</p> </li> <li> <p>Pull Phase: Lightly pull the hand (release it) until the elbow forms a right angle with the bottom (high elbow).</p> </li> <li> <p>Catch Phase: Pushing water is the main power phase; push until fingers touch the thigh to finish.</p> </li> <li> <p>Recovery Phase: Relax the hand while bringing it back to prepare for the next stroke. This phase should be slow, with a high elbow (lifted arm) if possible, then extend the arm straight forward (keeping the head low close to the arm) to pull the body forward.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Legs</strong>:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Avoid bending knees; generate force from the hips and thighs.</p> </li> <li> <p>Quick, small leg movements.</p> </li> <li> <p>Kick continuously, lightly, and steadily, gradually shifting to a 6-beat, 4-beat, or 2-beat kick rhythm based on body feedback.</p> </li> <li> <p>Since swimming relies largely on the legs tilting, allocate time for appropriate training.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Body Position</strong>:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Generally, maintain a straight body - streamline as much as possible.</p> </li> <li> <p>Keep the head low by looking down at the bottom (instead of forward) and keeping the chin close to the chest.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Hips</strong>:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Lightly engage hips during swimming. In speed swimming, the hips will continuously rotate to increase stroke frequency.</p> </li> <li> <p>The body rotation sequence should start from the hips → shoulders → head.</p> </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip-2">TIP</h5> <p>In open water or endurance swimming, start very lightly, relax, maintain a steady kick, breathe deeply, and inhale strongly (producing a hissing sound). These keywords are important reminders for myself before and during swimming.</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="b-survival-swimming">b. Survival Swimming</h3> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Treading Water</strong>: Use a combination of breaststroke/freestyle/flutter kick with hands to stay afloat in place.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Swimming with Head Up</strong>: You can swim breaststroke or freestyle with your head up. Freestyle with the head up is quite tiring, so for survival swimming, breaststroke with the head up is preferred. Unlike competitive breaststroke, head-up breaststroke maintains a 45-degree angle, with the head just above the water surface and hands pushing the water outwards.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Survival Dips/Relaxing in Place</strong>: Instead of keeping the head fully above water, allow it to sink for a few seconds of each cycle. Exhale while submerged and use hands, feet, or both to push yourself back up to breathe.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Sighting</strong>: Use either breaststroke sighting or a single head-up stroke during freestyle. This head-up stroke can be a low or high head lift (more tiring) to breathe. After this sighting phase, the position is often lost and becomes more tiring, so if you swim straight and well, the frequency of sighting will reduce, significantly improving speed.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="c-overcoming-the-swimming-slump">c. Overcoming the Swimming Slump</h3> <p>Swimming training can inevitably lead to the <strong>“blue”</strong>, where regular practice doesn’t seem to improve, persistent mistakes remain, or speed training hampers endurance and vice versa. Even though once you know how to swim, you will always know how, just not maintaining practice (e.g., &lt;1 session/week) means needing a few sessions to regain previous form. This is normal in sports training, and we should face it directly by:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Finding and trying different <strong>solutions and approaches</strong>.</p> </li> <li> <p>Setting <strong>realistic expectations</strong>, e.g., why swim in the first place?</p> </li> </ul> <p>Deciding to swim open water taught me several lessons. Open water swimming leads to <strong>more accurate swimming technique</strong> training. We need to learn many survival skills to <strong>stay safe and enjoy great experiences</strong>. A good open water location (lake, river) is better than a swimming pool because it doesn’t use cleaning chemicals, and there’s no lane congestion as in indoor swimming. Moreover, open water swimming is also less boring due to constantly changing scenery and views you can’t see from the shore or in a pool.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="5-discovering-a-passion-for-swimming-and-understanding-myself">5. Discovering a Passion for Swimming and Understanding Myself</h2> <h3 id="a-discovering-a-passion-for-swimming">a. Discovering a Passion for Swimming</h3> <ul> <li> <p>Swimming is a sport that can be enjoyed for longer than running. While I believe I can run until I’m 60, I think I can swim until I’m 70. Once you know how to swim, you can swim for almost your entire life.</p> </li> <li> <p>Swimming is an <strong>essential survival skill</strong> and a suitable sport for all ages.</p> </li> <li> <p>Additionally, swimming evenly impacts the entire body, leading to a better overall physique compared to long-distance running. Given its technical nature and the involvement of various muscle groups, proper training is crucial; otherwise, mistakes become difficult to correct later on.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="b-benefits-of-multi-sport-activities">b. Benefits of Multi-Sport Activities</h3> <p>Multi-sport activities are excellent for outdoor exercises, providing a refreshing experience and preventing boredom, unlike half or full marathons. I <strong>quit running marathons</strong> after participating in duathlons compared to <a href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/2023-lessons-learned/">2023 (every FM in each month in three last month of 2023)</a>. Engaging in an additional sport means acquiring new skills and experiences.</p> <h3 id="c-embracing-open-water-swimming">c. Embracing Open Water Swimming</h3> <p>Approaching open water swimming helped me understand myself and change my mindset about sports. I realized we can achieve amazing things by improving daily. I now <strong>prioritize improving performance</strong> over solely focusing on endurance, maintaining a much better sense of excitement, especially nearing the finish line. From my experience and observations, we shouldn’t exercise for too long, e.g., more than an hour a day. Currently, I maintain a “fun” run of <strong>5-8 km daily</strong>, with a long run on weekends of <strong>10-15 km</strong>, occasionally participating in events with a maximum distance of a half marathon.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/warrior_spirit.jfif-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/warrior_spirit.jfif-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b8_award_sport/warrior_spirit.jfif-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b8_award_sport/warrior_spirit.jfif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Participating in competition with great determination </div> <h3 id="d-from-fun-runs-to-warrior-mindsets">d. From Fun Runs to Warrior Mindsets</h3> <p>Post-Covid (2022), sports competitions in Vietnam have significantly increased in both quantity and quality across various provinces, inevitably leading to commercialization. Therefore, participating in competitions requires more selective choices and proper training plans. I believe entering a race with the mindset of fighting like warriors for a new Personal Record is essential. If previously fun runs and races aimed at finishing, now the goal is to <strong>fight hard in the race for a truly thrilling and rewarding experience</strong>. I think pursuing performance to explore personal limits is worthwhile but should be balanced with health considerations and choosing events that suit one’s physical condition and training plan. <strong>Winning a podium spot creates many opportunities and excitement</strong>, much more than participating just to finish.</p> <hr/> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip-3">TIP</h5> <p>As I have encouraged running, I should not neglect to encourage people to swim. Swimming is an essential survival skill and a highly effective and beneficial sport. It also serves as a great stepping stone for trying other outdoor sports like trail running.</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sports"/><category term="run"/><category term="swim"/><category term="life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My journey to win the first award in sports]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/2023-lessons-learned/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023"/><published>2023-12-31T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-31T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/2023-lessons-learned</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/2023-lessons-learned/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b7_2023/cover2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b7_2023/cover2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b7_2023/cover2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b7_2023/cover2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="1-change">1. Change</h2> <p>  <strong>Everything around us is constantly changing</strong>, from the environment and objects around us to the people we meet, new relationships, dream jobs or even our own thoughts, our bodies as we grow older.</p> <p>  As we grow up, <strong>our emotions as well as our eagerness gradually change over time</strong>. We can be happy just because we ate ice cream as children, worried about semester exams, or bored when we got bad grades. However, at some point, when we look back, we will no longer have that feeling, perhaps we will smile because we remember many things or perhaps because we have changed.</p> <p>  However, I think <strong>the most certain thing is the love of parents for their children</strong>. Before, I thought it was natural for parents to treat their children well. It wasn’t until we got married that I realized that was true, and I also realized that it’s natural for parents to treat their children well, but don’t expect to be treated the opposite way. That is, children should never treat their parents the way parents treat their children, and parents should not have the idea of ​​forcing their children to have those obligations.</p> <h3 id="a-characteristics-of-change">a. Characteristics of change</h3> <p>  <strong>Change is natural, inevitable, necessary</strong>. We go through stages - some notable, some nearly invisible to anyone but ourselves - and each one implies a necessary evolution. Without it we stagnate and things that stagnate are not really alive.</p> <p>  <strong>Change is frightening</strong> because it means leaving a place where you feel safe to go to a place you are not familiar with. Even if the place where you are at no longer works, even if it does not make you happy, your instinct is to stay because the act of leaving is processed in your brain as danger.</p> <p>  <strong>People change because of their circumstances and situations</strong>. People grow from their pains. People learn from their pain. People attain maturity from the worst phases they have undergone.</p> <h3 id="c-how-to-deal-with-change">c. How to deal with change?</h3> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip">TIP</h5> <p>Prepare yourself and taking proactive steps toward dealing with changes is a better way to take control and feel empowered.</p> </blockquote> <p>  Change often happens when you don’t expect it, so <strong>keeping an eye on the future and preparing yourself</strong>, at least mentally, might be helpful. Spend some time thinking about events that are coming up in the future that may lead to changes or disruptions.</p> <p>For example, if you know that you will be switching jobs, moving, or helping an aging parent, there are steps you can take now that will make those transitions less stressful. You might:</p> <ul> <li>Create checklists of things you need to do before the event happens</li> <li>Save money to avoid financial stress during times of transition</li> <li>Talk to career planning or financial professionals about your goals</li> <li>Discuss what will happen in the event of an emergency</li> <li>Make conscious choices about what you want to change in your life</li> </ul> <p>  <strong>When you are the one to initiate a change</strong>, there’s a stronger chance that you’ll feel like you have more control over what’s going to happen. It is often the unexpected changes in your life—whether it’s a job loss, divorce, or death of a loved one—that can leave you feeling afraid and unsure of what will happen.</p> <p>  One thing you should <strong>avoid doing is relying on avoidance coping techniques when you are confronted with stressful changes</strong>. When you use avoidance coping, you try to avoid the stress instead of dealing with it. While avoidance can sometimes reduce stress in the short term, it actually increases stress and anxiety in the long term. For example, avoiding coping might lead you to stay in a job you hate or a relationship that makes you unhappy because you are afraid of dealing with the stress of making a significant change in your life. Avoiding that change, however, will inevitably lead to more stress and unhappiness down the road.</p> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip-1">TIP</h5> <p>Change How You Think</p> </blockquote> <p>  <strong>The way you think about change plays a major role in determining how well you deal with it</strong>. Automatic negative thinking patterns can undermine your ability to focus on the positive. When negative thoughts bog you down, it is more challenging to have faith in your coping abilities. Shifting your mindset to be more positive and hopeful can help you feel more resilient and capable.</p> <p>  For example, if you see a change as something that is upsetting the balance of your life, chances are that you’re going to find it much more challenging to handle that change effectively. It’s more empowering to shift that perspective to focus more on your strengths and abilities to adapt. This way, you might see the positives that come out of the situation or believe in your ability to survive and thrive through change.</p> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip-2">TIP</h5> <p>Maintain Routines: Keep up your regular schedule as much as possible</p> </blockquote> <p>  When the world is changing all around you, <strong>holding on to some sense of normalcy</strong> can be a useful way to minimize stress and find comfort. Research has found that maintaining routines can help people get a better handle on symptoms of stress and anxiety.</p> <p>  Simple things like going to bed and waking up at the same time each morning can provide you with a sense of structure, even if it feels like other areas of your life are less predictable. Other activities you might want to incorporate into your daily routine that may help your mental well-being during times of transition include:</p> <ul> <li>Getting regular physical activity</li> <li>Eating healthy meals</li> <li>Getting plenty of rest each night</li> <li>Creating realistic daily goals</li> <li>Carving out moments for relaxation techniques like mindfulness or deep breathing</li> </ul> <p>  The routine that works for you depends on your own situation and needs. Think about the habits and daily activities that bring you comfort and peace and try to work some of those into your day, even if you are dealing with difficult or dramatic shifts in your life.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>Everything will change. Nothing will stay the same. Be prepared and adaptable.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h2 id="2-the-key-to-success-is-discipline-effort-and-daily-progressive-thinking">2. The key to success is discipline, effort, and daily progressive thinking</h2> <p>  I am currently quite satisfied with what I have: <strong>a pretty happy small family, being able to do my dream job and quite actively arranging to spend time playing my favorite sports</strong>. And I realized, the secret for me to achieve such <strong>“success” is discipline, perseverance and a better way of thinking every day</strong>.</p> <h3 id="a-running">a. Running</h3> <p>  From a person who was lazy and couldn’t run continuously for 15 minutes, I <strong>completed my first FM distance after 3 years of running</strong>. Of course, the achievement is nothing to talk about or brag about, what I think I get back the most is a positive change both physically and in my way of thinking. The detailed process and milestones I wrote in <a href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/my-first-marathon/">my previous blog</a>.</p> <p>  <strong>Discipline in running is shown in the fact that I will try to participate in jogging as much as possible, regardless of whether the weather is sunny, rainy, noon, evening or early morning</strong>. In addition, I will try to improve my running through increasing distance or increasing speed, thereby finding and challenging my limits. However, this process will encounter many problems sometimes unforeseen. It could be your own lack of endurance, discouragement when you don’t reach your goals, possible injuries during training or realizing you’re not really suitable for this sport. This requires a lot of patience to experiment and pursue before going the long way with this exciting subject.</p> <h3 id="b-swimming">b. Swimming</h3> <p>  During the summer of 2023, I made tremendous progress in swimming that I have not had for a long time. The starting point was <strong>knowing how to swim breaststroke about 100m</strong>. This summer I was determined to <strong>practice freestyle swimming to the fullest</strong>. As I learned at that time, swimming well is not easy, it takes a lot of time, because it requires flexible coordination of many parts. At the same time, there was a big difficulty that I chose to self-study. To overcome this problem, I had to go to the swimming pool regularly, every day setting small goals such as how many laps I could swim or correct my technique in certain areas. In addition, I often ask or take videos of myself to <strong>evaluate how the quality is at the end of the day and aim to correct little by little or learn new techniques for the next swim sessions</strong>.</p> <p>  <strong>Finally, after 2 summer months (June and July, 2023), I swam 1km in a continuous pool</strong>. This was an important milestone for me - and it was at that moment that I thought I had succeeded in “knowing how to swim freestyle”. I also had thoughts of participating in community events like Aquaman or Ironman to challenge myself when swimming in open water, but I realized that now is not the right time when I still have many things need to be improved. In addition, I’m wondering between swimming to exercise, just in the pool, and open water swimming which is somewhat more dangerous.</p> <h3 id="c-my-favorite-job">c. My favorite job</h3> <p>  Before becoming a Data Scientist like my current job, I was an electronics engineer. When I first graduated, I was <strong>wondering between working and going to graduate school/doing research with a scholarship</strong>. This decision stuck with me when I chose to work until I got married. Not because my family doesn’t let me go to school, but because I have more things to balance before making a decision. And so I’ve been working for more than 5 years, not because I no longer like going to graduate school, but <strong>now I’m more open to options, as long as it’s a good opportunity</strong>.</p> <p>  Going back to the story of changing industries, at that time the term <strong>“Machine Learning”</strong> was new in Vietnam and there were not many related jobs. My biggest motivation when switching jobs was the desire to apply cool things to solve real-life problems (than the work at the time). In addition, I also recognize more opportunities in software engineering than in electronics. After about <strong>20 interviews</strong>, I also got my first job as a <strong>Machine Learning engineer</strong> at <a href="https://www.3si.vn/">3S Intersoft</a> - an outsourcing company. I always secretly thank this first job, because I learned a lot from it and it also opened up many other opportunities for me so that the next job transition is not as difficult as the first. I learn more about industry job opportunities and choose the domain that is more suitable for me to go deeper.</p> <p>  <strong>My later jobs were all Data Scientist</strong>, but I didn’t have to go to interviews as much as the first time, but most of them were introduced. I feel fortunate that in the first years of working, I was able to work in large teams, to understand more about the work and responsibilities of the parties, as well as understand how to operate a team in a reasonable and effective way. Finally, in mid-2022, I was introduced to <strong>an opportunity to work remotely for an Australian company</strong> and I was accepted, and have remained until now. This job helps me be very proactive in terms of time, perhaps it is the most balanced and fair job I have had. I have learned more and done more for myself and my family, and feel somewhat lucky to have made the right choice and persevered with it.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="3-no-matter-what-i-do-for-me-a-happy-life-means-having-goals">3. No matter what I do, for me, a happy life means having goals</h2> <hr/> <h2 id="4-happiness-is-a-journey-not-a-destination">4. Happiness is a journey, not a destination</h2> <p>  <strong>Family happiness is achieved through joint efforts and building together</strong>, rather than being something attained after marriage or at a specific time like 5 or 10 years. Marriage is not an end, but a new beginning, and both parties must strive to nurture and preserve it, as it is not something that is inherently present.</p> <blockquote> <p>Happiness is not readily available, nor is it a fixed asset. It can also change as our mindset evolves.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p><strong>In summary, 2023 has been a successful and memorable year for me. I have had incredible experiences, achieved milestones, and made wise choices.</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="experience"/><category term="life"/><category term="skill"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My lessons learned in 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Marathon completion journey</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/my-first-marathon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Marathon completion journey"/><published>2023-09-10T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-10T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/my-first-marathon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2023/my-first-marathon/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/fm_finish-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/fm_finish-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/fm_finish-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/fm_finish.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>From the time I started :running: (December 2020) to the time of writing this blog, I have run <strong>about 300h, with a distance of 2900km</strong>, the longest distance is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marathon">Full Marathon</a>. These numbers will continue to increase.</p> <h2 id="1-how-did-i-come-to-run">1. How did I come to run?</h2> <h3 id="a-what-a-coincidence">a. What a coincidence!</h3> <p>I became addicted to running once I happened to participate in the company’s running race in December 2020. The race is held within 1 month, with 3 target levels of <strong>100, 150 or 200km</strong>. Of course, for someone who hasn’t run in a long time, I would choose 100km as my goal with an attitude of not expecting much. It is this attitude that has helped me discover many interesting points about running that I will share in the following sections.</p> <h3 id="b-why-do-i-like-to-run">b. Why do I like to run?</h3> <p>At first, I think it’s a satisfying, refreshing feeling similar to participating in any outdoor sport. Next, running allows me the freedom to explore the world on my own two feet without being dependent on any means. This also helps me to generate many ideas of interesting trips to explore to new and distant lands. The final reason is that health is largely improved by running:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>I live a healthier life</strong>. Thanks to running, I gradually formed a habit of taking care of my health more, starting to pay attention to my heart rate, practicing regular breathing, practicing foot landing, proper arm swing or warm-up thoroughly to avoid injury.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>My fatty liver level II is now gone</strong>, there is no blood fat and the excess level of uric acid is also very low. Of course, to achieve these results also thanks in part to the diet.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Realize your weight loss goals more effectively</strong>. Here’s my weight change since I started running (updated weekly) and I think everyone should have one. I have lost 5kg in the first 2 months and maintained it until now.</p> </li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/weight_tracking-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/weight_tracking-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/weight_tracking-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/weight_tracking.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My weight tracking </div> <h3 id="c-why-should-everyone-run">c. Why should everyone run?</h3> <p>First of all, I think running is a natural human instinct. People can run a lot with very few injuries. Second, running is a low-cost sport, very easy to start, and has no limits. You can run in many different terrains, from plains to hills, to the coast… anywhere you want to go and explore. You can run with basic sneakers or sandals, a sneaker or even run barefoot in the clothes you wear to bed.</p> <p>Running is like any other sport, very essential for every human life which helps to release stress, keeps them fit and fine, improve their general health, to make friends, or to enjoy social recreation and entertainment. In addition, running can help us change our mindset in a positive way, we will be more active, we will not be afraid to walk in increasingly congested traffic conditions like today.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="2-training-process">2. Training process</h2> <h3 id="a-achievements-in-the-running-race">a. Achievements in the running race</h3> <ul> <li>First week: my first 2km and 5km</li> </ul> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/2k-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/2k-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/2k-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/2k.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/5k-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/5k-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/5k-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/5k.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <blockquote> <p>The first week of the race, I had a hard time maintaining a steady, continuous running speed for a period of time. Reaching the first 2km up to the 5km in a row is a huge achievement for me. Later when I ran longer, I realized that this was the best moment, when the body was not too tired and kept a lot of excitement. The image on the right here are my running results measured using the Strava app installed on my phone.</p> </blockquote> <ul> <li>Second week: my first 10km</li> </ul> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/10k-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/10k-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/10k-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/10k.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <blockquote> <p>Next, I ran the first 10km in the second week, but the running process was still interrupted by my resting rhythms due to my inexperience with long runs.</p> </blockquote> <ul> <li>Third week: my first 15km</li> </ul> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/15k-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/15k-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/15k-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/15k.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <blockquote> <p>Once I was able to run 10km, I set a goal to “graduate” from the Half-Marathon (21km). To do that, I conquered 15km in the 3rd week. At this time, I paid attention to warm up carefully and replenish water during the run to be able to run continuously. My average Pace has improved significantly around 6:15 to 6:30 per km.</p> </blockquote> <ul> <li>Fourth week: 21km</li> </ul> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/21k-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/21k-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/21k-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/21k.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <blockquote> <p>I finally finished the HM run at the end of December 2020. Even though I hurt my leg and couldn’t walk properly, and even had to crawl up the stairs when I finished running, the feeling of achieving my goal was amazing. I finished the company’s race with a total of 150km passed and officially became addicted to running.</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="b-my-first-official-community-half-marathon">b. My first official community Half Marathon</h3> <p>After completing the first HM in my life, I have maintained about 3 running sessions a week, each session averaging 5-7km and longer on weekends. I started signing up for community races so that my running results were more <strong>“official”</strong> instead of being measured by phone. However, due to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COVID-19">Covid-19 epidemic</a>, the tournament was postponed several times; I can’t go to Ha Long to run until July 2022, even though I registered more than 1 year ago. The prize that I participated in is the <a href="https://vm.vnexpress.net/ha-long-2022">Vnexpress Marathon Amazing Halong</a> organized by <a href="https://vnexpress.net/">Vnexpress newspaper</a>. The tournament was organized very professionally, from receiving the BIB to completing the distance, all were fully supported. This makes me very satisfied when I spend money and time participating in the tournament.</p> <p>To prepare for this tournament, I maintain a long run of 10-15km per week in the morning to match the actual running time within 1 month before the official run date. My goal is to finish <strong>HM within 2 hours (HM sub2)</strong>.</p> <p>Finally, I have officially completed the Half Marathon within 2 hours from the time of starting the hole in <strong>December 2020 (so far 1 year and 8 months)</strong>. The most challenging is to cross <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A3i_Ch%C3%A1y_Bridge">Bai Chay bridge</a> with a height of up to 32m. Thoughts of giving up but being buffed to 4:30 pace when going downhill is a great motivation for suffering later.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/hm_finish-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/hm_finish-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/hm_finish-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/hm_finish.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My first official Half Marathon at Vnexpress Marathon Amazing Halong 2022 </div> <p>Although completing HMs exceeded my expectations, every time I finish, I always think 21km is more than enough. I should not make it difficult for myself. However, something prompted me to do FM on a special occasion. This led to the following results.</p> <h3 id="c-my-first-full-marathon">c. My first Full Marathon</h3> <p>After completing the HM sub2 in Ha Long, I tried to run the Full Marathon twice on <strong>my birthday (October) and Christmas (December)</strong>. However, I failed. The reason is that after 21th km, I felt my feet hurt and my body was not prepared for this great distance.</p> <p>Just like experienced runners shared: <strong>“FM is not like running 2 times HM”</strong>. The more you increase the distance, the more tired your body will be and your excitement will decrease.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/1st_fm-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/1st_fm-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/1st_fm-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/1st_fm.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My first Full Marathon </div> <p>In the end, whatever comes must come. Refusing to run HM forever, I tried again at the beginning of the new year 2023 and finished my first Full Marathon. As such, I <strong>completed the 1st FM journey on the 3rd and previous 5 HM attempts</strong> with:</p> <ul> <li>2 liters of electrolytes</li> <li>1 banana :banana:</li> <li>2 cereal bars and 1 loaf of bread :bread: (unexpectedly hungry in the last few kilometers).</li> </ul> <p>Although I have completed the Full Marathon, I must admit that for me HM is the best distance with moderate effort and keeping the excitement throughout the journey.</p> <p>Some time later, I also wanted this achievement to be more official when participating in an award ceremony. Once again, I completed the FM in Ha Long the same way I did the HM distance.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b3_marathon/fm_finish-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/fm_finish-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b3_marathon/fm_finish-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b3_marathon/fm_finish.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My first official Full Marathon at Vnexpress Marathon Amazing Halong 2023 </div> <hr/> <h2 id="3-some-memories-and-lessons-learned">3. Some memories and lessons learned</h2> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Should I buy specialized equipment to start running?</strong></p> <ul> <li> <p>It is not necessary to invest too much money in the first place. I think we should start simple until we’re really passionate: simple clothes, simple tracking method (by mobile phone, watch), simple shoes. You will have many options for each device you bring, so calmly consider the best fit.</p> </li> <li> <p>Take the example of shoes, if you consult, you will see many different opinions to choose shoes depending on your budget, durability, beauty, speed boost, or sandals will be appropriate. I have tried running sandals for different distances (5k, 10k, HM) and found that running sandals would be the best option for short distances, high speed. However, with a long running distance (&gt;15km), running in sandals is not good for feet with shoes, easily leading to foot pain and injury. Once passionate, besides consulting reviews, taking the time to experiment to choose the right equipment will be very interesting and not wasted.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Something to do before and during the run</strong>. The experience that I learned after having swollen feet and having to abstain from walking for 1 week are some important notes as below:</p> <ul> <li>Before running, warm up for at least 5 minutes, especially the leg area</li> <li>Limit speeding too quickly (meaning rapid changes in heart rate), especially when the body is not used to the pace (for example, you have not run in a long time), avoid injuries such as sprains.</li> <li>Keep your heart rate consistent: keep your heart rate within your physically appropriate heart rate zone. I usually keep my running heart rate steady between <strong>130-165 (mostly 140-150)</strong>. In the long run, a real-time heart rate monitor will be worth owning.</li> <li>Provide adequate water: With thick runs, I find 3-5km of water buff to be reasonable. This I have tried many times before giving specific numbers, you can completely experience and have your own numbers.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Should you practice long strides?</strong></p> <ul> <li>My normal running stride is only <strong>97-105 cm</strong>. I feel envious when I know that some pacers can reach a stride of <strong>120-140 cm</strong> and spend time training to improve their stride. As a result, I increased my pace a bit, but in return I felt uncomfortable running and sore feet. After researching more about this issue, I found that most people agree that increasing stride is not necessary, let the running posture be the most natural.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <hr/> <p>In short, for me, running is a process of self-discovery and self-understanding. You may not need a teacher but can learn through trial and error and find the right fit on your own.</p> <p>I think every one of us, young or old, should :running:. Let’s start simple: short distance, low speed, simple outfit. Let running gradually positively affect you naturally by maintaining the habit of wearing shoes every day.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sports"/><category term="run"/><category term="life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My journey to complete the first Full Marathon]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Minimalism</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/minimalism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Minimalism"/><published>2022-09-30T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-30T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/minimalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/minimalism/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b6_minimalism/cover-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b6_minimalism/cover-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b6_minimalism/cover-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b6_minimalism/cover.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimalism">Minimalism</a> is not only an interesting lifestyle but also brings many benefits, especially in an era of so many choices like today’s life.</p> <h2 id="1-what-is-minimalism">1. What is Minimalism?</h2> <p>Minimalism is <strong>a lifestyle practice focused on minimizing distractions</strong> that keep you from doing what matters to you, which is the process of sifting through things that do not create value, so that we no longer have to waste energy on those things. From there, we focus on living with the things that create the most value for us.</p> <p>We only have a certain amount of energy, time, and space in our lives. In order to make the most of it, we must be intentional about how we’re living each day.</p> <blockquote> <p>Minimalism is also not a one and done project.</p> </blockquote> <p>We could use minimalism as a continual practice to ensure everything in our lives is working for us in our vision, not against us and to make substantial changes in careers, home, lifestyle, buying behaviors, etc.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="2-benefits-of-a-minimalist-lifestyle">2. Benefits of a minimalist lifestyle</h2> <h3 id="a-minimalism-is-interesting">a. Minimalism is interesting</h3> <p>Minimalism does not mean living a miserable life, not knowing how to enjoy it. Moreover, minimalism also does not mean owning as few things (furniture, clothes, assets) as possible. Instead, a minimalist life <strong>focuses on things that bring a lot of value, emotion</strong>. Let us enjoy what we have.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b6_minimalism/idiom-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b6_minimalism/idiom-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b6_minimalism/idiom-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b6_minimalism/idiom.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Realistically, <strong>everyone should be a minimalist</strong>. Who doesn’t want to be surrounded by everything that’s important and nothing that weighs us down? It makes a ton of sense when you start to think about it.</p> <p>Note that you don’t have to call yourself a minimalist either. The way I see it, minimalism isn’t my identity or some goal to achieve; it’s a tool used as part of the framework of doing more of what matters.</p> <h3 id="b-more-time-more-energy-more-options">b. More time, more energy, more options</h3> <p>Time and energy are limited. Minimalism will <strong>save you time and energy</strong>, thereby <strong>opening up many new options</strong> for us. Because <strong>choice is probably the greatest benefit in this life</strong>. We get to live the life we ​​want - that’s happiness.</p> <h3 id="c-minimalism-is-an-effective-tool-for-living-an-intentional-life">c. Minimalism is an effective tool for living an intentional life</h3> <p>In the end, minimalism is less about owning fewer items and <strong>more about actively making choices on what kind of things truly matter to you</strong>. It is not about not having enough information to choose from, but about choosing the most appropriate after evaluating other options.</p> <p>We exist in a society that creates false value on <strong>owning more stuff and having no time to use them much</strong>. The constant pursuit of bigger and better is an endless cycle. There will always be a nicer car to buy, a bigger boat, a larger home, and or a faster private jet. Did you know that there’s a website for billionaires to shop? Yeah. It never ends.</p> <p>It may seem like an overwhelming challenge at first, but as you untangle the life you built around owning more things, you’ll find the stress disappearing and the world starting to slow down. Those choices you make will begin to build muscle that will fundamentally change the way you live your life.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="3-practice-minimalism">3. Practice minimalism</h2> <p>The best way to practice minimalism is to <strong>start with the smallest things in our daily lives</strong>. Starting small is the best way to get started on something that feels like a big change.</p> <h3 id="a-find-one-thing-remove-it-from-your-home">a. Find one thing, remove it from your home</h3> <p>You can research yourself into oblivion, but the best way to get started is to just find one thing you don’t need anymore and let it go (by selling or donation).</p> <blockquote> <p>Minimizing material desires will help you have more space, money, focus on quality things.</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="b-stop-the-influx-of-new-things">b. Stop the influx of new things</h3> <p>The next immediate step is to <strong>stop the influx of new things that you don’t actually need</strong>. Whether that means logging out from Amazon or not going to the mall anymore, take steps to prevent yourself from purchasing new things that will continue to clutter your home. Create some guiding questions about what types of things add value to your life and which types of things don’t add value. Beware of the <a href="https://www.breakthetwitch.com/false-first-step/">False First Step</a>—buying something for the aspirational version of yourself instead of taking a minimally viable action using what you have already.</p> <h3 id="c-start-changing-mindset">c. Start changing mindset</h3> <p>Along with the practice of minimizing, your mindset will also gradually change. You will know enough to be happy, know what is right, what is important and what should be prioritized.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Minimize relationships</strong>: If you’re not comfortable with a relationship, cut them off</li> <li><strong>Minimize things to do</strong>: Your to-do-list should not cover everything</li> <li><strong>Minimize goals</strong>: We cannot achieve everything at once</li> <li><strong>Minimize concerns</strong>: don’t worry about what do others, newspapers, radio stations, neighbors… say</li> <li><strong>Minimalism in investing</strong></li> </ul> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>Obviously, <strong>minimalism is an interesting lifestyle</strong>, a useful tool to get the life we ​​want. Let’s start with minimalism from the most everyday things and change your mindset to live a life worth living.</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="experience"/><category term="life"/><category term="skill"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalism - an interesting lifestyle with many benefits]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is a SMART goal enough?</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/smart-goal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is a SMART goal enough?"/><published>2022-09-22T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-22T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/smart-goal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/smart-goal/"><![CDATA[<swiper-container keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/cover-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/cover-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/cover-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/cover.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/1.why-set-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/1.why-set-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/1.why-set-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/1.why-set-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/2.types-of-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/2.types-of-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/2.types-of-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/2.types-of-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/3.goal-categories-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/3.goal-categories-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/3.goal-categories-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/3.goal-categories.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/4.s-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/4.s-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/4.s-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/4.s-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/5.m-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/5.m-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/5.m-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/5.m-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/5.m-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/5.m-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/5.m-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/5.m-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/6.a-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/6.a-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/6.a-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/6.a-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/7.r-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/7.r-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/7.r-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/7.r-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/8.t-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/8.t-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/8.t-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/8.t-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/9.examples-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/9.examples-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/9.examples-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/9.examples.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/10.life-goals-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/10.life-goals-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/10.life-goals-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/10.life-goals.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/11.personal-opinions-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/11.personal-opinions-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/11.personal-opinions-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/11.personal-opinions.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/12.is-smart-goal-enough-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/12.is-smart-goal-enough-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/12.is-smart-goal-enough-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/12.is-smart-goal-enough.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/13.do-you-really-need-smart-goal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/13.do-you-really-need-smart-goal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/13.do-you-really-need-smart-goal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b5_smart_goal/13.do-you-really-need-smart-goal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="experience"/><category term="life"/><category term="skill"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[SMART goal methodology]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self-learning - The most important life skill</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/self-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-learning - The most important life skill"/><published>2022-09-20T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-20T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/self-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/self-learning/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b4_self_learning/cover-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b4_self_learning/cover-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b4_self_learning/cover-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b4_self_learning/cover.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autodidacticism">Self-learning (or self-study, self-taught)</a> is a way of learning about a subject that involves studying alone at home, rather than in a classroom with a teacher. Expanded, self-study is the ability to actively research, find solutions and draw experiences for life’s problems.</p> <h2 id="1-why-is-self-learning-the-most-important-life-skill">1. Why is self-learning the most important life skill?</h2> <p>Learning is subject to a lot of changes from the living environment such as epidemics, lockdowns, congested roads, floods. Our education nowadays is going online and we all are aware of the fact that this method is not that helpful for students. <strong>Self-Study is a great weapon to use time positively</strong>.</p> <p><strong>Self learning is important</strong> because it switches the focus of learning from the teachers to the students themselves. Self-study allows students to take learning at their own pace, focusing on areas they are most interested in (or want to understand a bit better). This helps reduce feelings of frustration, anxiety, or boredom that students may struggle with in a classroom setting. It is a great time for every student to <strong>explore new things on their own</strong>, and they can also <strong>learn new topics according to their interest</strong>. This is a time where they have to learn everything <strong>related to their books and outside of the books on their own</strong> because there are no schools and classes are going on where teachers are present to help them. In this time students have to <strong>think about their future and career</strong> and have to <strong>start giving time to their self studies</strong> that will help them in future for cracking exams and in their life also.</p> <p>After you graduate and go to work, your time will not be much left for you to go to class. Instead, you will need to take advantage and arrange a reasonable time to supplement professional knowledge as well as other skills necessary for your work and life. Therefore, self-study is very important and the <strong>university (or college) is a very good environment for practicing self-study</strong>.</p> <p>Overall, self-study will give you many benefits to develop:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Saving and self-control on time</strong>. You will not lose time for commuting, packing, etc., as long as your study is effective.</li> <li><strong>Get to know your best friend</strong>. The self-study process will help you better understand your best friend’s strengths, weaknesses, and habits. These things will help you a lot in the process of making the right choices in life.</li> <li><strong>Cultivate a can-do mindset</strong>. When you have a problem, you will actively seek information and come up with a solution and learn from it. Over time, you will feel confident in your ability to solve the problem. And beyond that, you will feel freer, more active in life.</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>It can be said that self-study is a basic and necessary skill for each of us, it is also the foundation for the good development of other skills in life.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h2 id="2-how-to-effectively-self-learn">2. How to effectively self-learn?</h2> <h3 id="a-suggestions">a. Suggestions</h3> <p>There are a few suggestions to help you practice better self-study, specifically:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Find a good place to study and minimize distractions</strong>. Finding a good location to study is one of the most important elements of studying well. Look for a quiet place with minimal distractions—someplace where you’ll be able to focus, and won’t be interrupted by loud sounds or people who constantly want your attention. Moreover, you should also turn off or isolate distracting devices from your working place.</li> <li><strong>Set study goals for each session</strong>. Set study goals for each session of studying you have. These can be time-based or content-based. For example, you might aim to study for two hours, or review three chapters of your textbook—or both. Don’t be too harsh on yourself if you didn’t get through as much as you had planned; sometimes studying can take longer than expected. Keep taking well-spaced breaks, and schedule another study session.</li> <li><strong>Practice, practice and practice</strong>. Practice tests have been long seen as useful tools to help students learn and retain information. Besides revealing gaps in knowledge and reducing exam anxiety, being tested makes us retrieve information from memory—a powerful, study-backed way of holding onto information we’ve learned. Practice is also the best way to master your skills and form lasting habits.</li> <li><strong>Use your own words</strong>. Expressing an idea in your own words increases your understanding of a subject and helps your brain hang on to information. After you read a section of text, summarize important points by paraphrasing.</li> <li><strong>Reward and Take care of yourself</strong>. At the end of the day, your brain is an organ in your body—take care of it by taking care of yourself. Get regular exercise, eat well, don’t overdrink, get good sleep, and take care of your mental wellbeing. Whether trying or rushing, remember that learning is a long-term path, whoever is more durable will have the advantage.</li> <li> <p><strong>When should I start practicing self-learning?</strong></p> <p>I think self-study is the starting point of all skills and should be acquired <strong>as soon as possible</strong>. I plan to instill this mindset in my children very early on.</p> </li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b4_self_learning/idiom-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b4_self_learning/idiom-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b4_self_learning/idiom-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b4_self_learning/idiom.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>To be effective in self-study, you need both <strong>internal and external support</strong>. On the outside are things related to your surroundings such as places, friends, equipment, learning tools, etc. and inside is the motivation that aligns with your goals. These will enable you to realize the two main principles of being productive: <strong>focus and practice</strong>.</p> <h3 id="b-reference-myself">b. Reference myself</h3> <p>I myself began to know and build self-study skills since university. I taught myself programming, taught myself English. Of course, before “using” these skills, I used to feel scared and thought that I couldn’t learn it or it wasn’t really suitable for me. And then I ask myself the same question, <strong>explore different learning methods for each skill</strong>, <strong>spend time on trial and error</strong>, and most importantly, <strong>practice</strong>.</p> <p>I quite like the saying <strong>“Life is a series of choices”</strong>. Choices can happen every day in our lives and if we have the ability to analyze and evaluate, the ability to make the right decisions will be higher. Some examples of choices can include: buy or rent a house, a 1-bedroom or 2-bedroom house, which school should I send my child to, should I go to graduate school after graduation, which company should I work at, etc. Therefore, I also practice <strong>analytical skills</strong>, evaluate to make the right choice and this skill also affects my career choice. My current job also involves a lot of data analysis and building solutions from data, and I am quite happy with this job. And I think that achievement is largely due to self-study.</p> <p>I taught myself through <strong>watching other people work to understand how it works</strong>, seeing the good to learn, the negative to avoid. With current technology, we can easily find this information through books, newspapers or social networking sites.</p> <p>I <strong>learned from my own experience through repeated trial and error</strong>. Since graduating from college, I have changed jobs a few times. The first time I changed jobs, I applied to <strong>20 companies</strong>, only <strong>4 companies called for an interview</strong> and <strong>only 1 offer</strong>. And of course, I chose that offer. The 2nd time is <strong>8-10 companies</strong> and the <strong>3rd and 4th times</strong> are recommended by colleagues as well as applying for a few more companies that I love. Looking back on that journey, it can be seen that the number of options has decreased as my experience has increased as well as I have understood myself better to make more suitable choices. Here are some questions I’ve had answers to after job changes:</p> <ul> <li>Is it better to go to graduate school or to work?</li> <li>Work for a private or public company? Company outsourcing or products?</li> <li>Small company or big company? Vietnamese or foreign companies?</li> <li>Self-study certificate or take an after-school class</li> </ul> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>In conclusion, I think self-study is a good and very important life skill. If someone asked me for advice, I would probably tell them: Build the habit of learning from people and from yourself as soon as possible.</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="experience"/><category term="life"/><category term="skill"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My self-study experience]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some interesting facts about Data Science</title><link href="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/datascience-funfacts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some interesting facts about Data Science"/><published>2022-04-16T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-16T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/datascience-funfacts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/datascience-funfacts/"><![CDATA[<p>Data science and related disciplines, including data analytics, remained a top priority. These domains are interesting and in great demand today.</p> <p>If you’ve read <a href="#https://manhitv.github.io/blog/2022/how-to-become-a-data-scientist/">my previous blog</a>, you can see that there is much to prepare for a job in data science. Beside many interesting things about data science, there may be several others that might surprise you.</p> <h2 id="1-trends-in-job-market">1. Trends in job market</h2> <p>With all the optimism (and big potential salaries listed in news articles) around data science, it’s easy to see why it presents attractive career opportunities, particularly as the range and scope of data science job titles continues to expand. But as a new entrant to the field, it’s important to have a realistic, nuanced view of where the data science market is heading for the next couple years and adjust accordingly.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_0-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_0-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_0-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_0.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Trends impact the data science field </div> <p>Given these trends, it’s important to understand that it may be hard to initially differentiate yourself from the other resumes on the pile to get into the final round of interviews. You need to have some strategies to help you stand out, which is needed in this new, competitive data science environment.</p> <h2 id="2-can-you-be-a-data-scientist-withwithout">2. Can you be a data scientist with/without?</h2> <h3 id="a-can-you-be-a-data-scientist-without-programming">a. Can you be a data scientist without programming?</h3> <p>It’s <strong>possible to do a lot of data work using only Excel, Tableau, or other business intelligence tools that have graphical interfaces</strong>. Although you’re not writing code, these tools claim to have much of the same functionality as languages such as R or Python, and many data scientists do use them sometimes. But can they be a complete data science toolkit? We say no. Practically, very <strong>few companies have a data science team where you wouldn’t need to program</strong>. Without programming, there will be a limited number of solutions that you could deliver to customers. For example, you can not deploy a machine learning model to run continuously.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Some advantages of programming over using BI tools </div> <h3 id="b-do-i-need-a-phd-to-get-a-data-science-job">b. Do I need a PhD to get a data science job?</h3> <p>PhDs are degrees that <strong>take many years to obtain</strong> and that focus on training students to become professors. You have to <strong>spend years doing research to find a new method or solution to a problem that’s very slightly better than the previous one</strong>. You publish to academic journals and move state-of-the-art research forward in an extremely specific area. But little work that a data scientist does is like academic research.</p> <blockquote> <p>A data scientist cares much less about finding an elegant, state-of-the-art solution and much more about quickly finding something that’s good enough</p> </blockquote> <p><strong>A fair number of data science job posts require a PhD</strong>. But the skills acquired in a PhD program are rarely what’s needed for the job; usually, the PhD requirement is a signal from the company that the position is considered to be prestigious. The <strong>material you can learn from a master’s or undergraduate degree program will suit you fine for the vast majority of data science jobs</strong>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> You probably don't need a PhD to get a data science job </div> <p>Also, <strong>getting a PhD incurs huge opportunity cost</strong>. If it takes seven years to graduate, you could have been working at a company for seven years instead, getting better at data science and making far more money.</p> <p>Finally, the decision is dependent on you. You could go get a PhD and then be a data scientist, but don’t let anyone tell you that you need this degree.</p> <h2 id="3-which-skills-are-the-most-precious-for-a-data-scientist">3. Which skills are the most precious for a Data Scientist?</h2> <p>A data scientist’s main responsibility is to try to <strong>imagine all of the possibilities</strong>, address the ones that matter, and reevaluate them all as successes and failures happen. That is why—no matter how much code I write—<strong>awareness and familiarity with uncertainty are the most valuable things</strong> I can offer as a data scientist.</p> <p>Like an explorer, <strong>a modern data scientist typically must survey the landscape, take careful note of surroundings, wander around a bit, and dive into some unfamiliar territory to see what happens</strong>. When they <strong>find something interesting, they must examine it, figure out what it can do, learn from it, and be able to apply that knowledge in the future</strong>. Although analyzing data isn’t a new field, the existence of data everywhere—often regardless of whether anyone is making use of it—enables us to <strong>apply the scientific method to discovery and analysis of a preexisting world of data</strong>. This is the differentiator between data science and all of its predecessors.</p> <h2 id="4-will-data-science-disappear">4. Will Data Science disappear?</h2> <p>Underlying the question about whether data science will be around in a decade or two are two main concerns: that the <strong>job will become automated</strong> and that <strong>data science is overhyped and the job-market bubble will pop</strong>.</p> <p>It’s true that <strong>certain parts of the data science pipeline can be automated</strong>. Automated Machine Learning (AutoML) can compare the performance of different models and perform certain parts of data preparation (such as scaling variables). But these tasks are just a small part of the data science process. You’ll <strong>often need to create the data yourself</strong>, for example; it’s very rare to have perfectly clean data waiting for you. Also, creating the data <strong>usually involves talking with other people, such as user experience researchers or engineers</strong>, who will conduct the survey or log the user actions that can drive your analysis.</p> <p>Regarding the possibility of a pop in a job-market bubble, a good comparison is software engineering in the 1980s. As computers grew cheaper, faster, and more common, there were concerns that soon a computer could do everything and that there would be no need for programmers. But the opposite thing happened, and now there are <strong>more than 1.2 million software engineers</strong> in the United States (<a href="http://mng.bz/MOPo">http://mng.bz/MOPo</a>). Although titles such as webmaster did disappear, more people than ever are working on website development, maintenance, and improvement.</p> <p>We believe that <strong>there will be more specialization within data science</strong>, which may lead to the <strong>disappearance of the general title data scientist</strong>, but many companies are still in the early stages of learning how to leverage data science and there’s plenty of work left to do. Moreover, as data sicentists become more senior, they should focus on un-automative tasks and interpersion skills such as preparing proper data, communicating, interpreting results with customers effectively.</p> <h2 id="5-what-do-junior-data-scientists-frequently-get-wrong">5. What do junior data scientists frequently get wrong?</h2> <p>I think junior data scientists <strong>assume people are going to automatically recognize the value in their work</strong>. This is especially common <strong>among data scientists who come from academic backgrounds</strong>. We tend to get really wrapped up in everything being superthorough and following the scientific method. While this is important in academia, just working hard is not enough in the industry. <strong>The way that you communicate is what gets people to recognize the value of your work.</strong></p> <h2 id="6-do-you-always-try-to-explain-the-technical-part-of-data-science">6. Do you always try to explain the technical part of data science?</h2> <p>It <strong>depends on how much the stakeholder wants to be involved</strong>. Some project managers do not want to be involved in anything technical. If you just said <em>“This is not working right now”</em>, they would take that at face value. Other project managers want to know every detail, and what you might feel that they do tend to get a little overwhelmed. Some people want you to check in on a regular basis and tell them what’s happening, and even if they know that they don’t understand, they just want to feel in the loop. So I’ll just <strong>make sure that they feel in the loop</strong>.</p> <h2 id="7-data-science-competitions-and-real-life-projects-are-different">7. Data science competitions and real life projects are different</h2> <p>Getting success in a data science competition (e.g. through an online platform like <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/">Kaggle</a>) may give a boost to one’s confidence so much that one starts thinking of landing a data science career. There is quite a lot of difference between a competition and a real-life scenario.</p> <p>Data science competition websites, such as Kaggle or <a href="https://www.drivendata.org/">Drivendata</a> are great places for practicing machine learning, but that’s not all of data science.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Compare some characteristics of Data Science competitions with real-life projects </div> <p>So, it would be safe to say that competitions do give a fair practice for data science. But it is not enough. You need to get your hands dirty and work in live real-time projects to know the correct essence of data science.</p> <h2 id="8-more-data-does-not-always-mean-more-accuracy">8. More data does not always mean more accuracy</h2> <p>Suppose we have a dataset with the exact number of minimum data that is needed to make a correct analysis. This would be an ideal dataset. Now if we add some more data, the entire dataset will need to be reconstructed considering the new set of data as well. While reconstructing, there will be a need to clean the new data and spend time to understand their deviation from the existing set, if any.</p> <p>Even after the new data is cleaned and merged to the existing ideal dataset, there is a possibility that some new element is still dirty but unidentified. This will lead to an overall degradation of the final result or analysis. In this case, lesser data was surely better than more data. Hence, more data doesn’t mean more insight or more value addition. Using smart data is the key.</p> <h2 id="9-some-others-funfacts">9. Some others funfacts</h2> <ul> <li>Assumption about Data Scientist job</li> </ul> <p><img src="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_4.png" alt="image alt text"/></p> <ul> <li>Assumption about Deep Learning</li> </ul> <p><img src="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_5.png" alt="image alt text"/></p> <ul> <li>Assumption about Big Data</li> </ul> <p><img src="/assets/img/b2_ds_funfacts/image_6.png" alt="image alt text"/></p> <h2 id="10-references">10. References</h2> <p>[1] <a href="https://www.manning.com/books/build-a-career-in-data-science"> Build a career in Data Science</a></p> <p>[2] <a href="https://www.manning.com/books/think-like-a-data-scientist"> Think like a Data Scientist</a></p> <p>[3] <a href="https://www.bls.gov/ooh/computer-and-information-technology/software-developers.htm"> Statistic of software engineer jobs in the U.S.</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="work"/><category term="datascience"/><category term="career"/><category term="fun"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some interesting facts about Data Science]]></summary></entry></feed>